Guide to the Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture Records, 1996-2008 RL.00113
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture records
1996-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture
RL.00113
11.5 Linear Feet
In 1996, Bitch: Feminst Response to Pop Culture was created by Lisa Jervis, Benjamin Shaykin, and Andi Zeisler. After having a hard time finding critiques of sexism in pop culture in magazines and self published zines, they decided to make their own. Their goals are to write about sexism in pop culture, propose alternatives, and promote pop products that are pro-woman and pro-feminism. Chiefly production records for magazine issues, including drafts and edited copy for articles, laser printer and resin-coated paper page layouts, and color proofs. Includes editorial correspondence, research files, meeting notes, promotional and subscription material, audio cassette and mini-cassette tapes, VHS tape, mini-disks, color and black-and-white photographs, negatives, and color transparencies. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
6000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001. Additions were received in 2002, 2003, 2007, and 2008.
Historical Note
In 1996, Bitch: Feminst Response to Pop Culture was created by Lisa Jervis, Benjamin Shaykin, and Andi Zeisler. As feminists and pop culture addicts, Lisa and Andi shared not only experiences as interns at Sassy magazine, but also an interest in creative, humorous, and biting analysis of sexism in pop culture. After having a hard time finding this in magazines and self published zines, they decided to make their own. The goals of their magazine were to point out the everyday sexism of popular culture, propose alternatives, and celebrate pro-woman, pro-feminism pop products. Bitch magazine includes critiques of magazines, TV, films, advertising, and other pop culture areas. Also included are new book and movie reviews and interviews with feminist pop culture makers.
Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture is published by B-Word Worldwide, a non-profit independent, feminist media organization in the making. In addition to publishing this magazine, B-Word hopes to become a larger mutlimedia organization by branching out to have a larger online presence, as well as book publishing and audio and video production.
Collection Overview
Chiefly production records for magazine issues, including drafts and edited copy for articles, laser printer and resin-coated paper page layouts, and color proofs. Includes editorial correspondence, research files, meeting notes, promotional and subscription material, audio cassette and mini-cassette tapes, VHS tape, mini-disks, color and black-and-white photographs, negatives, and color transparencies. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Negatives (photographic); Feminism -- Periodicals; Color transparencies; Color photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- Correspondence; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States; Women's periodicals, American; Proofs (printed matter); Periodical editors -- United States -- Correspondence; Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture; Jervis, Lisa; Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Zeisler, Andi
- Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture Records, 1996-2008, 17 boxes
  - Accounting records, 1996 (Box 1A)
  - Subscription information, 1996 (Box 1A)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 1A)
  - Submissions, 1996-1999 (Box 1A)
  - Bitch: Feminist Response to Pop Culture benefit party invite, 1997 (Box 1A)
  - Press clips, 1996-1998 (Box 1A)
  - Research material and drafts of issue No. 1, 1996 (Box 1A)
  - Research material and drafts of issue No. 2, 1996 (Box 1A)
  - Drafts of issues 1 and 2 (Box 1A)
  - Drafts of Vol 2., No. 2 - Vol. 3, No. 3, 1996-1999 (Box 1B)
  - Galley of Vol. 3, No. 3, 1999 (Issue 9) (Box 2)
  - Drafts of No. 10 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Original folder lists this as issue 4.1 which is the same as No. 10.
  - Drafts of No. 11-12, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Reader's letters, 1997-2001 (Box 2)
  - Color transparencies, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Cover wrappers of Vol.2, No. 3 and Vol. 3, No. 1, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Issues of Vol. 1, No. 1 - Issue No. 14, 1996-2001 (Box 2)
  - Photos and negatives, 1996 and undated (Box 3)
  - 9 cassette tapes and 7 micro-cassette tapes, 1998-1999 and undated (Box 3)
  - Resumes, 1996, and 1998-2001 (Box 3)
  - Subscription renewal and ad rates, undated (Box 3)
  - Research material, 1997-2002 (Box 3)
  - Printing estimates, 1998-2001 (Box 3)
  - Budget drafts - FY2002 (Box 3)
  - Clean copy of No. 11, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Submissions, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Drafts of No. 13-14, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Corrected proofs, No. 14, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Clean copy, No. 14-16, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
  - Corrected proofs, No. 17-18, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Drafts of No. 15-16, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    Do not go by what is at the bottom of the proofs. Even though proofs say No. 15, articles were published in issue No. 17. Arranged here by what was actually published.
  - Drafts of issues ranging from No. 16-21, 2001-2003 (Box 5)
    Again, do not go by what is at the bottom of proofs. Arranged by what was actually published and what corresponds to that issue/number.
  - Correspondence with distributors/publishers, 1996-2000 (Box 5)
  - Insertion orders, 1999-2002 (Box 5)
  - Reader's letters, 2000-2004 (Box 6)
  - Pitches and research material, 2003 (Box 6)
  - Design and layout, No.22-25, 2003-2004 (Box 6)
  - Budget Sheets, FY2003-04 (Box 6)
  - Shipping gallies, 1999-2002 (Box 6)
  - Proofs, No. 22-23, 2003-2004 (Box 6)
  - Proofs No.23, 2004 (Box 7)
  - 1 VHS tape, 1997 (Box 7)
  - 1 audiocassette tape, undated (Box 7)
  - 5 minidisks, 2004-2006 and undated (Box 7)
  - Research material, 1995-1997, and 2001-2002 (Box 7)
  - Lineups, No. 29-34, 2005-2007 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 7)
  - Pitches 2002-2003 (Box 7)
  - Letters to the Editor, 2001-2004 (Box 8)
  - Slides, undated (Box 8)
  - 2 Contact sheets from benefit, undated (Box 8)
  - Proofs, No. 25-28, 2004-2005 (Box 8)
  - Proofs No. 28-31, 2005-2006 (Box 9)
  - Proofs No. 31-33, 2006 (Box 10)
  - BITCHFest reviews, 2006 (Box 10)
  - Photocopy of first pass proofs of BITCHFest (Box 10)
  - Drafts of BITCHFest (Box 11)
  - First pass proofs of BITCHFest (Box 11)
  - Proofs of BITCHFest (first, second, and third passes) (Box 12)
  - Laser prints of BITCHFest, 2006 (Box 13)
  - Photos from Vol. 1, No. 1, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Laser prints of Vol. 1, No.1, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Linos of Vol. 1, No. 2 - Vol. 2, No. 2, 1996-1997 (Box 13)
  - Color proofs of covers Nos. 8, 10, 11, and 14, 1998-1999 and 2001 (Box 13)
  - Laser prints of No. 14, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Transparencies, No. 17, Summer 2002 (Box 14)
  - Awards 1999, 2001, 2003 (Box 14)
  - Journal/meeting notes, 2001-undated (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 2003-2008 (Box 14)
  - Cover art for Nos. 20, 21, 35, 36, and 41, 2003, 2007-2008 (Box 14)
  - Essays on feminist publishing, 2004 and undated (Box 14)
  - Layout, No. 29, 2005 (Box 14)
  - Queries and pitches, 2006-2008 (Box 14)
  - Proofs, No. 35, Spring 2007 (Box 14)
    First folder contains pages of layout labeled No. 33. It is actually for No. 35.
  - Proofs, No. 35, Spring 2007 (Box 15)
  - Proofs, No. 37, Fall 2007 (Box 15)
  - Bear Deluxe No. 25, Summer 2007 (Box 16)
    Contains interview with Andi Zeisler and Debbie Rasmussen.
  - Clean copy, No. 38, Winter 2008 (Box 16)
  - Proofs, No. 39, Spring 2008 (Box 16)
  - Proofs, No. 41, Fall 2008 (Box 16)
  - Photographs, negatives, contact sheets, undated (Box 16)
  - Promotional material, undated (Box 16)
  - Research material, undated (Box 16)
  - Cover art and design, Nos. 20, 21, 31, 41, 2003, 2006, 2008 (Box 17)
  - 2006 wall calendar (Box 17)
  - Poster from show and silent auction, 2007 (Box 17)
  - Meeting notes, undated (Box 17)